Finding Aid for Sally Howell papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sally Howell papers
1986-2005
1994-1997
Howell, Sally
1.6 linear feet
2016013 Aa 2
Sally Howell is an associate professor of history and Arab American Studies at the University of Michigan-Dearborn. The collection includes papers and photos dealing with her work in ACCESS (Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services); as well as various lectures and museum exhibitions that she has prepared.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Sally Howell (donor no. 10840 ), in November, 2015.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
TThe collection is open without restriction.
Sally Howell received her B.A. in Middle Eastern Studies from Davidson College in 1985. She then worked with ACCESS in Dearborn, MI from 1987 to 2000, serving as Cultural Arts Director as well as consultant and grant writer. In 2002 she was awarded a M.A. in American Culture from the University of Michigan and in 2009 was awarded a Ph.D. in American Culture from the University of Michigan.
From September of 2009 to May of 2015, Howell held the position of Assistant Professor of History at the University of Michigan- Dearborn, working in the Center for Arab American Studies. As of May 2015 she has begun work as Associate professor.
Howell's teaching and research interests include: history of Islam in the United States, Arab American history and culture, Detroit history and culture, citizenship and migration, and The War on Terror and its impact on Arab and Muslim Americans.
Arranged into four series: Museums, Lectures and Tours; Grants and Awards; Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services; and Business Directories.
Included are documents and photos relating to Howell and her work with Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS) in Southeast Michigan. These documents range from plans for anniversary events for ACCESS, lecture tours Howell gave, museum exhibitions, administrative information on ACCESS, and miscellaneous information pertaining to Detroit and its Arab American population.
Subjects:
Arab Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services.; Communities--Michigan--Detroit; Howell, Sally.; Immigrants--Michigan--Detroit.; Minorities--Michigan--Detroit.; Museum exhibitions--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Dearborn. Department of History.; University of Michigan--Dearborn--Faculty.Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Commercial directories.; Photographs.
- Museums, Lectures, and Tours
  The Museums, Lectures, and Tours series (0.6 linear feet, 1994-2001) contains papers on Howell's various speaking engagements and museums exhibitions. Venues include the National Museum of American History (NMAH), The Castellani Art Museum of Niagara University, The Museum of the City of New York (MCNY) and the Michigan State University Museum (MSUM). Various folk art exhibitions and tours are also highlighted, as well photos and slides of Arab Americans in Detroit and relevant museum exhibitions.
  - NMAH exhibit photos (gallery), 1995 (Box 1)
  - NMAH final text, undated (Box 1)
  - NMAH exhibition plan, 1996 (Box 1)
  - NMAH miscellaneous, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian list of artifacts, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Michigan State University (MSU) loan and ethics forms, undated (Box 1)
  - English 679, (college course), 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Cultural forum participants, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Castellani, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Castellani showing, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Niagara University, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Folkart and fieldwork, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Folkart contacts, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Tour AT&T, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Tour support, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Tour support letters, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Tour work, undated (Box 1)
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) tour, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Tour-Smith collection, undated (Box 1)
  - Canaw, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Nabeel slides, 1995 (Box 1)
  - AWM, 1995 (Box 1)
  - MSUM miscellaneous materials, undated (Box 1)
  - MSU labels, 1997 (Box 1)
  - MCNY, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Arab Theatrical Arts Guild (ATAG), 2001 (Box 1)
  - Museum pamphlets, 1993-1998 (Box 1)
  - Arab Detroit photos, undated (Box 1)
  - Jelia photos and slides, undated (Box 1)
- Grants and Awards
  Grants and Awards series (0.4 linear feet, 1987-2001) consists of the varied funding sources appealed to by Howell on behalf of ACCESS. The organizations included are The National Endowment for the Humanities, the National Endowment for the Arts, Lila Wallace, and Skillman funds. In addition, a recognition letter for the Glen Taggart award is included.
  - Sumnist/ National Endowment for the Arts (NEA), 1997 (Box 1)
  - Glen Taggert award, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Lila Wallace, 1997 (Box 1)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 1997 (Box 1)
  - Unlikely funding sources, 1987-1994 (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller 96, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller fund, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Skillman, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Strategic plan, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Balch Institute, 2000 (Box 1)
- Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services
  The ACCESS series (0.3 linear feet, 1987- 2005) includes administrative records, as well has the plans for anniversary dinners and papers pertaining to Howell's film Tales from Arab Detroit.
  - Promotional materials, 1994; 1995 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
  - Public comments, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Arts program books, 1987-1996 (Box 1)
  - Dinner, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Dinner art, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Imani Ali, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Detroit (DET) history, undated (Box 1)
  - Tales from Arab Detroit materials, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Arab World Mosaic, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Archive project, undated (Box 2)
  - Archival ideas, 2005 (Box 2)
- Business Directories
  Business Directories series (0.3 linear feet, 1993-2005) contains editions of Arab American yellow pages from Southeast Michigan.
  - JEI business directory, 2000 (Box 2)
  - American Arab Business Directory
    - 1993-1997, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - 2005 (Box 2)
Related Materials
Bentley Historical Library holds Tales from Arab Detroit, a documentary film co-created by Howell, and Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services records.